A Guide to the George E. Uhlenbeck papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA125
Rockefeller Archive Center
George E. Uhlenbeck papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1925-1988
Rockefeller Archive Center
Uhlenbeck, George Eugène, 1900-1988
FA125
10.6 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
George Uhlehbeck was born in Batavia, Dutch East Indies' (today Jakarta, Indonesia) in 1900 and died on October 31, 1988 in Boulder, Colorado. He received his Ph. D. degree in 1927 from the State University of Leyden in the Netherlands. While pursuing his graduate studies, he collaborated with Samuel A. Guidsmit in the discovery of the electron spin phenomenon. This concept of an electron's characteristic spin angular momentum about a specific axis has proved to be a cornerstone of basic atomic theory. Uhlenbeck's later research was primarily concerned with the statistical an kinetic theory of the equilibrium and non-quilibrium phenomena of physical systems.
Dr. Uhlenbeck joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1927 and was named professor of theoretical physics in 1939 and Henry Cahart University Professor of Physics in 1954. He served as professor of theoretical physics at the University of Leiden from 1935 to 1939. During World War II, he worked at the Radiation Laboratory at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. In 1961 he joined the faculty of Rockefeller University where he helped to establish the University's distinguished theoretical physics faculty. He retired from Rockefeller University in 1974 but continued his interest in physics, serving as both mentor to younger physicists and as an appraiser for articles submitted to scientific journals.
Among Dr. Uhlenbeck's many honors were the Max Planck Medal of the German Physical Society (1964), the National Medal of Science (1977) and the co-recipient of the Wolf Prize (1979). He received honorary degrees from Rockefeller University (1976), Notre Dame University (1953), Case Institute (1960), the University of Colorado (1968) and Yeshiva University (1969). He was elected a member of the National Academy of Sciences in 1955. He was also a member of the American Philosophical Society, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Association for the Advancement of Science and the American Physical Society, serving as president from 1959-1960.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological and alphabetical order.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 U600
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: biographical materials, correspondence, manuscripts, speeches, notes, reprints, and subject files.
Statistical mechanics; General relativity (Physics); Physics; Goudsmit, Samuel Abraham, 1902-; Pais, Abraham; American Institute of Physics; Strauss, Lewis L.; American Physical Society; Rockefeller University
- Biographical Material, 1961-1989, undated; 1; 0.4 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Subjects include curriculum vitae, honors received, bibliographical lists or articles, books, reviews, lectures and speeches, obituaries, American Physical Society memorial services and archival copies of photographs.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Biographical Material, undated 1961 1964 1967 1970 1974-1975 1977 1979 1983 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photos (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Biographical Material-List of Dr. Uhlenbeck's Articles in Journals, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical Material-List of Dr. Uhlenbeck's Books and Reviews, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Material-List of Books that Dr. Uhlenbeck reviewed, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biographical Material-List of Published Lectures and Speeches, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Material-List of Widely Circulated and Partially Published Reports and Lecture Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Honors, Awards (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Obituaries, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Physical Society Memorial Symposium in Memory of G. E. Uhlenbeck, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal correspondence, 1961-1962 1964 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Else Uhlenbeck Correspondence (wife), 1985-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1943-1988, undated; 2; 2.8 Cubic Feet
  Includes personal and professional correspondence. Correspondents include Samuel Goudsmit, A. Pais, Eugene Wigner and H. Woolf which include his memories of Einstein in Leiden.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent name.
  - Aaserud, Finn, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Abramovici, Alex, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Abrams, Al, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Adair, Robert K., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Adomian, George, 1961-1962 1964-1965 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - American Journal of Physics, 1966 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Amsterdam-Rotterdam Bank, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Araki, Huzihiro, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Aulick, F. C., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "B" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Belkin, Samuel, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - W. A. Benjamin, Book Publishers, 1961-1962 1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Bethe, Hans, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - de Boer, J., 1961 April 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - de Boer, J. May, 1963-1967 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - de Boer, P.C.I., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Borowitz, Sidney, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bowen, Dwain B., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Brayshaw, David D., 1965-1966 1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Brink, Frank, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Brittin, Wesley, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Brookhaven National Laboratories, 1961-1963 1965 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Brown, Laurie M., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Burger, J. M., 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Cantore, Enrico, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Carter, Charles C., 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Case, Kenneth M., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Casimir, H. B. G., 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Chang, N. P., 1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Chang, T. S., 1965 1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Chen, J., 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Chen, Wang Min, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Choh, Soon Thak, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Cohen, E. G. D., 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Cohen, E. G. D., 1963-1964 1969-1972 undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Columbia University, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Compagner, A., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Corkern, Robert W. Jr., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Cowling, T. G., 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Crane, H. R., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "D" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Dorfman, J. Robert, 1961-1964 1966 1969-1970 1979 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Dresden, Max, 1963-1964 1974 1978 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Duffendack, O. S., 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dutta, M., 1973 1975 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dvoretzky, Aryeh, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "E" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Emch, Gerard G., 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Emrich, Raymond J., 1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica, 1960-1961 1967 1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Evan, William M., 1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Evans, Robert W., 1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "F" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Fahrney, D. S., 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Fisher, M., 1968 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Fiszdon, W., 1971-1972 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Fixman. Marshall, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Foch, James, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Foch, James, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Foch, James, 1968-1969 1972 1977-1978 undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Foldy, Leslie, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Ford, George W., 1961-1965 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Ford, Joseph, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Fowler, Richard G., 1976-1977 1979 undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Fox, Ronald F., 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Fox, Ronald F., 1967-1973 1975-1979 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Frenkel, V., 1971 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Frenkiel, Francois, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Frenkiel, Francois, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Frenkiel, Francois, 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Frenkiel, Francois, 1971-1974 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Friedberg, Richard, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Friedman, Ephraim, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Frohlich, H., 1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fujita, S., 1966 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fuller, Robert, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "G" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Galison, Peter, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Garber, M., 1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Gebbie, H. A., 1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Gerharz, R., 1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Gilde, Hans-George, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Gilson, Greyson, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Glaser, Donald A., 1962 1976 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Goldberger, M. L., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Goldhaber, Maurice and Trudy, 1979, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Good, R. H. Jr., 1974 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Gordon, William L., 1979 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Goudsmit, Samuel A., 1943 1962-1963 1965 1969-1972 1975 1981 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Greco, Frank, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Green, Melville S., 1970-1971 1973 1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Greenspan, Martin, 1974 1976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Greider, K. R., 1979 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Griffith, Wayland C., 1974 1976 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - de Groot, Sybren R., 1961-1965 1968 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Guernsey, Ralph, 1961-1963 1969 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Gugelot, P. C., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1961-1965 1967 1970 1972-1973 1976 1979 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Guth, Eugene, 1975 1978 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Guttman, James, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "H" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Haidemanakis, E. D., 1970 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - van den Handel, J., 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Harary, Frank, 1961-1962 1964 1968-1977 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Havens W. W. Jr., 1979 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Healy, James, Bruce, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Hecht, Charles E., 1961 1963-1964 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - de Heer J., 1980 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Hemmer, Per C., 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Hemmer, Per C., 1963 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Hemmer, Per C., 1964-1965 1969 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Hendry, John L., 1978 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Henlein, Lore, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Hermans, J. J., 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Hesketh, Ross, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Holton, Gerald, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Houston, William V., 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Hund, Friedrich, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Hynes, J. T., 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - International Biographical Center, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Jackson, H. W., 1979 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Jaffe, Robert L., 1981 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Jancovici, B., 1963 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Jehle, Herb, 1964 1976 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Jost, Res, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - American Journal of Physics, 1969 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Journal of Chemical Physics, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Journal of Fluid Mechanics, 1971 1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Journal of Mathematical Physics, 1965 1974 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 'K' Name Letter Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Kac., Mark, 1958 1963-1966 1969 1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - van Kampen, N. G., 1971 1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Keizer, Joel E., 1973 1975-1976 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Keller, Frederick J., 1980 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Kestin, Joseph, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Kincaid, John M., 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Klein, Martin, 1962 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Klein, Martin, 1968 1970-1972 1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Klein. Oscar, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Koch, H. William, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Koga, Toyoki, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Kohler, Wolfgang, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Koninklijke Nederlandse Akademie van Wetenschappen, 1968 1970 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Konopinski, Emil, 1964 1979 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Krimm, Samuel, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Krisch, A. D., 1978 1980 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Kursunoglu, Behram, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Kurtz, Paul, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "L" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Lamb, Willis, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Landman. U., 1976 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Landsberger, Frank, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Lannutti, Joseph, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Leaf, Boris, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Lebowitz, Joel L., 1968 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Leuchtag, H. R., 1976 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Lieb, Elliot H., 1974 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Lin, C. C., 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Lind. David A., 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Linnett, J. W., 1966 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Lipschutz-Yevick, Miriam, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Lorentzen, Hans L., 1963 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Lorentzen, Hans L., 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Lorentzen, Hans L., 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Lovitts, Hannah W., 1978 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Lowdin, Per Olav, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Luders, G., 1982 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - "M' Name Letter Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Macorini, Edgardo, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Madden, Edward H., 1975 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Maric, Z., 1979 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Maxfield, Robert, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Max Planck Institute, 1967-1970 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Max Planck Institute, 1971 1978-1979 1981 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Mayer, Joseph E., 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Mazur, Paul, 1962-1964 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Mazur, Peter, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - McCarty, Macyln, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - McFarland, Marvin W., 1974 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - McGraw-Hill Book Company, Daniel N. Lapedes, editor, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Meeron, Emmanuel, 1960-1961 1963-1964 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Mehr, Jagdish, 1969 1972 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Melehy, Mahmoud A., 1974 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Menaker, Walter, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Misra, S. G., 1975 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Moldauer, Peter, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Mondadori Publishing Company, 1973-1974 1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Moore, William R., 1974 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Murphy Thomas, 1964-1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Musher, Jeremy I., 1961-1964 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "N" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Nagel, Ernest, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1966-1967 1979 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Neumark, Gertrude F., 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - New York Academy of Science, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Niels Bohr Institute, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Nishina, Yoshio, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Noakes, G. R., 1977 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Nobel Prize, 1964 1969 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Nonnenmacher, Theo, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - North Holland Publishing Company, 1961-1964 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - North Holland Publishing Company, 1965-1966 1968-1972 1974 1977 1980 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - O'Neill, Patrick E., 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Ong, Rudi, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Opdahl, R. Brown, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Oppenheimer Prize Committee, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - "P" Names Letter Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Pais, Abraham, 1962-1982 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Pauli, Wolfgang, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Perkeris, C. L., 1965 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Phillipson, Paul E., 1975 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Physical Review Letters, 1972-1973 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - The Physical Review, 1975 1977 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Princeton University Press, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Pusey, Nathan, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Putterman, Seth, 1974-1978 1981 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Quintas, Louis V., 1965 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "R" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Rajagopal, A. J., 1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Ratliff, Floyd, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Reyseger. W., 1962 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Rittner, E. S., 1961-1967 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Roper, L. David, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Rota, Gian-Carlo, 1974 1979 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Rothen, Alexandre, 1975 1977 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Henry Russel Lecture Dinner, 1961-1963 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Rutgers, A. J., 1964 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - "S" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Saar, Robert A., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Sabin, John R., 1979 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Sachs, Mendel, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Sands, Richard H., 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Sapirie, S. R., 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Sathe, Dileep V., 1976 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Schensted, Irene V., 1963 1966 1977 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Schwinger, Julian, 1975 1977 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Scully, Marian O., 1977 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Seaborg, Glen T., 1962 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Segre, Emilio, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Seitz, Frederick, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Siegal, Armand, 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Siegert, Arnold J. F., 1961 1964 1970 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Simmons, R. O., 1974 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Sloan Foundation, 1970-1971 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Smith, Alice Kimball, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Smith, Sam C., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Springer-Verlag, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Spruch, Grace M., 1963-1964 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Stolzenburg, Klaus, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Stout, J. W., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Stoyanov, S., 1974 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Swinney, Harry L., 1976 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Szu, H. H., 1971 1973-1976 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Tellegen, B. D. H., 1973 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Tempeley, H. N. V., 1964 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Throop, Gerald, 1965-1969 1972 undated (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Trappeniers, N. J., 1972 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Trigg, George L., 1975 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Trotter, Robert, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Uehling, Edwin A., 1965 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Union of Concerned Scientists n.d. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - University of Illinois at Champaign-Urbana, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - The University of Michigan, 1978-1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Van Gleck, J. H., 1977 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Van Ootjen, D. J., 1964 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Veltman, M., 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Verwey, E. J. W., 1961 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Vineyard, George H., 1980 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Vogel, J., 1964 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - "W" Name Letter Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Wahl, Charles E., 1965 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Waldman, L., 1972 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Wang, Cheng Shu, 1956 1972 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Wannier, G. H., 1965 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Ward, J. C., 1960 1964 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Weart, Spencer, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Wehausen, John V., 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Weiner, Charles, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Weisskopf, Victor, 1976 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Wells. Gene L., 1977 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Wergeland, H., 1966-1967 1972 1979 undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Wigner, Eugene P., 1963 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Wilder, R. L., 1977 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Wilson, Robins L., 1976 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - The Wolf Prize, 1979-1981 1984 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Woolf, Harry, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Wu-Ta-You, 1961 1963 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Yeshiva University, 1962 1965 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Zaidi, Mumtaz, 1971-1972 1975 1981 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Ziff, Robert, 1975-1978 1980-1982 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Zorn, Jens, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1962 1964 1970 1972 1976 1977 undated (Box 8, Folder 33)
- Subject Files, 1958-1981; 3; 2 Cubic Feet
  Subjects include Dr. Uhlenbeck's correspondence as president of the American Physical Society, material related to the controversy over Admiral Lewis B. Strauss' speech before the Society and documents pertaining to the American Institute of Physics and the Institute's efforts to establish a Center for the History of Physics.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by subject.
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Air Force Office of Scientific Research-Office of Aerospace Research, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - American Institute of Physics, 1959-1960 March (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - American Institute of Physics, 1960 June-September (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - American Institute of Physics, 1950 October-December (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - American Institute of Physics, 1961 January-March (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - American Institute of Physics, 1961 May-July 1964 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - American Institute of Physics-A.I.P. Advisory Committee on History and Philosophy of Physics, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - American Institute of Physics-A.I.P. Advisory Committee on History and Philosophy of Physics, 1963-1964 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - American Institute of Physics-A.I.P. Advisory Committee on History and Philosophy of Physics, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - American Institute of Physics-A.I.P. Advisory Committee on History and Philosophy of Physics, 1964-1966 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - American Institute of Physics-A.I.P. Advisory Committee on History and Philosophy of Physics, 1970-1973 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - American Institute of Physics-A.I.P. Advisory Committee on History and Philosophy of Physics, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - American Institute of Physics-A.I.P. Advisory Committee on History and Philosophy of Physics, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - A.I.P. Center for the History of Physics-Scripts: The Beginning of Nuclear Energy - The Discovery of Nuclear Fission, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - A.I.P. Center for the History of Physics-Program 3. The Living History of Physics - Tape 1. The Discovery of Nuclear Fission, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - A.I.P. Center for the History of Physics-Program 3. The Living History of Physics - Tape 2. The Discovery of Nuclear Fission, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - American Mathematical Society-Res Jost Manuscript, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - American Physical Society, 1965 1958 January 1959-April 1959 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - American Physical Society, 1959 May-June (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - American Physical Society, 1959 June-August (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - American Physical Society September, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - American Physical Society, 1959 October-November (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - American Physical Society, 1959 November-December (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - American Physical Society, 1960 January-March (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - American Physical Society, 1960 April-November (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - American Physical Society Divisions Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - American Physical Society Reorganization Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - American Physical Society-Strauss Affair, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Debye, P., 1965 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica-J. Robert Oppenheimer Article, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Extraterrestrial Research Center-NASA Apollo Applications Program, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Harvard College Board of Overseers, 1963-1965 February (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Harvard College Board of Overseers June, 1965-1968 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Harvard College Board of Overseers-Visiting Committee Meeting, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Harvard College Board of Overseers-Visiting Committee Meeting, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Harvard College Board of Overseers-Visiting Committee Meeting, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Harvard College Board of Overseers-Committee Assignments, 1963-1967 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Harvard College Board of Overseers-Committee Assignments, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Dannie Heineman Prize, 1958-1962 1966 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - International Mathematical Union, 1960-1961 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Physics, 1960-1961 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Physics, 1961-1962 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - International Union of Pure and Applied Physics, 1963-1965 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Advisory Board for the Interscience Monograph and Tract Series, 1961-1962 1964 1966 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Koninklijke Nederlandse Akademie van Wetenschappen (Royal Netherlands Academy of Sciences and Letters), 1961-1962 (Box 12, Folder 4)